A Guide to the John L. Heatwole Personal Papers, 1973 -1995: SC 0101
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
John L. Heatwole Personal Papers,
1973 - 1995
Special Collections, James Madison University
Heatwole, John L., 1948-2006
SC 0101
.84 cubic feet; 2 boxes
John L. Heatwole Personal Papers, 1973-1995, consists of one Hollinger box and one flat box of items such as correspondence, exhibit notices, consignment contracts, magazine articles, photos, and sketches relevant to Heatwole's work as an artist and lecturer.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated by John L. Heatwole in December 1987 and September 1995.
Bio/Historical Note
John L. Heatwole (1948-2006), born in Washington D.C., served in the U.S. Marine Corps and worked at the Library of Congress until 1974, when he and his wife, Miriam, relocated to the Shenandoah Valley. Heatwole originally took a job as a woodcarver with the Virginia Craftsmen Furniture Company in Harrisonburg, Va., and three years later he opened his own woodcarving shop in Bridgewater, Va. Heatwole drew on folklore and family sotries as inspiration for his wood carvings. Using only hand tools and a secret color staining process, Heatwole became widely recognized as a local artist of note. In addition to artist and woodcarver, he was also locally known as a tour guide, historian and folklorist in the Shenandoah Valley. Throughout his lifetime he sat on various committees and boards related to both art and history, and received many awards for his work. He chaired the Rockingham County Bicentennial Committee and in 1991 he was the first Virginian to display art in the National Capital Rotunda. Heatwole also authored several books relating to superstitions, folkways, and the Civil War.
Scope and Content
John L. Heatwole Personal Papers, 1973-1995, consists of one hollinger box and one flat box of items such as correspondence, exhibit notices, consignment contracts, magazine articles, photos, and sketches relevant to Heatwole's work as an artist and lecturer. The collection is arranged into five series: Diaries, Letters, Media, Miscellaneous, and Oversize Materials.
Series 1, Diaries, 1979-1995, consists of four bound diaries arranged into two folders. The content of these diaries is mainly relevant to his business and art.
Series 2, Letters, 1976-1987, includes incoming letters from students, fellow artists, clients, the Dow Agency, and Neiman-Marcus. Many letters are pertinent to exhibits, events, and lectures Heatwole participated in.
Series 3, Media, 1973-1989, includes magazines and newsletters containing articles about Heatwole, photocopies of newspaper clippings about the artist, and a 1989 WVPT video of an interview with the artist.
Series 4, Miscellaneous, 1976-1987, contains a variety of items relevant to Heatwole's art, as well as events and activities in which he participated. The series includes two issues of Fine Woodworking Magazine which contain articles and reviews written by Heatwole. A few items of crrespondence from the publisher relevant to the articles are housed with the magazines. The series also holds drafts of articles by Heatwole; business documents such as sale receipts, consignment contracts, and deeds of gift; photographs of the artist and his woodcarvings; and event memborabilia such as public notices of exhibits, programs from events, and photocopies of a visitor register form from an exhibit of Heatwole's work.
Series 5, Oversize Materials, 1976-1987, is an oversize flat box containing posters advertising Heatwole's work on display at Neiman-Marcus and a variety of Heatwole's sketches.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by topic into five series: Diaries, Letters, Media, Miscellaneous, and Oversize Materials.
Related Material
John L. Heatwole Collection of Shenandoah Valley History, 1802-1901, SC 0092, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va.
Bibliography
Heatwole, John L. John L. Heatwole: The Word Gatherer, Oral History Inteview. By Carol Maureen DeHart. Staunton, Va.: Lot's Wife Publishing, 2007.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Heatwole, John L., 1948-2006; Cheek, Leslie, 1908-; Artists -- Virginia -- Biography; Folk artists -- Virginia -- Biography; Wood-carvers -- Virginia -- Biography; Wood-carving; Wood-carved figurines; Art -- Philosophy
Genre and Form Terms:
Diaries; Letters (correspondence); Photographs
- Series 1: Diaries, 1979-1995
  - Diary, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1983-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series 2: Letters, 1976-1987
  - Artists and Students, 1981-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cheek, Leslie, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clients, 1978-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dow Agency, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lectures, 1976-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Neiman-Marcus, 1979-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series 3: Media, 1973-1989
  - Articles about Artist, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1973-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - WVPT Interview, 1989
- Series 4: Miscellaneous, 1976-1987
  - Published Articles by Heatwole, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Article drafts by Heatwole, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Business Documents, 1977-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Event Memorabilia, 1976-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photos, 1979-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series 5: Oversize Materials, 1976-1987
  - Neiman-Marcus Poster, 1981 (Box OV 1, Folder 1)
  - Neiman-Marcus Posters, 1981-1982 (Box OV 1, Folder 2)
  - Neiman-Marcus Posters, 1983-1984 (Box OV 1, Folder 3)
  - Sketches, 1976-1983 (Box OV 1, Folder 4)
  - Sketches, 1984-1987 (Box OV 1, Folder 5)
  - Sketches, undated (Box OV 1, Folder 6)